<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/nargar/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/nargar/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-04-08T21:47:17+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/nargar/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nargar</title><subtitle>Feel free to get in touch at nargarvlh@gmail.com. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Vlh Exp</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/nargar/2022/04/06/vlh-exp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vlh Exp" /><published>2022-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/nargar/2022/04/06/vlh-exp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/nargar/2022/04/06/vlh-exp.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-experience-with-debilitating-illness-long-haul-and-potential-treatments&quot;&gt;My experience with debilitating illness (long haul) and potential treatments&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1470777639313-60af88918203?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=1740&amp;amp;q=80&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-intro&quot;&gt;1. Intro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea behind writing this post is to share my personal experience with long haul, to shed light on what the condition is, and what having it really &lt;strong&gt;means&lt;/strong&gt; for the sufferer, with the aim of going beyond simply listing the symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally I wish to provide some information about vaccine long haulers, how they are similar to covid long haulers, and the use of the covid vaccine in the context of covid long haul, as evidenced by the available literature, online surveys, and the experience of myself and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living with illness this severe has been an eye opener for me, and interesting in many ways, not exclusively negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The illness has transformed my life for the time being. I’m 30 years old, male, and I identify as a software developer, hard worker, and weight lifter. For now, &lt;em&gt;identifying&lt;/em&gt; as being those things is all I can do, I cannot live them. During this last year I’ve spent most days &lt;em&gt;lying in bed, unable to think&lt;/em&gt;, or get anything meaningful done. I’ve been at a loss when it comes describing my situation to friends and family, and I hope this post may be of some help there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will start with some pessimism (or realism), but end the post on a tentatively positive note, as I believe there is hope for recovery, for myself and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re in a hurry, depending on your interests, I recommend reading either just the sections about &lt;em&gt;my experience&lt;/em&gt; (if you’re someone who likes me), or, if interested in long haul, then jump straight to section #2 and read about covid- and vaccine long haul. Including especially the section on what the symptoms really &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; for these people, though I expect my own experience should be insightful there too. The connection between covid vaccination and covid long haul is complicated and curious, and well worth reading about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re dealing with long haul and looking for ideas on how to improve your symptoms and regain function I suggest you stay tuned for the next post I intend to write. I don’t expect anyone except people dealing with these conditions would be even remotely interested in reading that. Although I’d say, &lt;em&gt;somewhat&lt;/em&gt; objectively, that the material is really interesting. I am not and will not be handing out any medical advice. Following in my footsteps would be dumb and potentially dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-own-story&quot;&gt;My own story&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a computer science graduate. I was on the dean’s list at university and I worked overtime roughly every day for the few years following my entrance to the job market, post-graduation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My salary went up quicker than anyone I knew from uni, and I derive a lot of my sense of self-worth from my ability to think logically, and work hard. I worked out 4 days per week and was fairly healthy prior to last year. I had been dealing with some fatigue but I’d gotten it under control with treatment for ADHD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the start of summer 2021 I’d describe my life as pretty good. My health was looking better. I was running my own company with two of my friends, where I worked as a software consultant and developer. Our biggest client, a sizeable nordic hardware store chain, was happy with the value we were delivering for them, and VPs from abroad had shown interest in the software we were developing with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great/beautiful girlfriend who I love, and appreciate still. She had supported me through some of my fatigue and related mood issues previously. It looked like everything was working in my favour at the time, in both my work and personal life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;onset-of-illness-and-symptom-progression&quot;&gt;Onset of illness and symptom progression&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things took a swift turn for the worse in June 2021, when I suddenly got very ill. I received both doses of my covid vaccination that month, the last dose by the end of the month, on the 29th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was nothing concerning about my first dose, as evidenced by my showing up for the second one three weeks later. After completing my vaccination I experienced various debilitating (and confusing) symptoms, the most meaningful of which I still struggle with today (8th of April 2022, ~10 months later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The symptoms seemed dumbfounding to me. I was sure I had to be one of a handful of people at most, who was dealing with anything like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t connect the symptoms to the vaccination then, in part because I’d also recently started a type of blood pressure medication for ADHD, which I thought might be playing a role. Since then I’ve seen so many people describe the exact same set of (fairly unqiue) symptoms, with the same post-vaccination onset, that there’s little doubt in my mind that the vaccine was the cause for me. Add to this the curious connection to covid long haul, which I’ll describe briefly in section #2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should state here that I realise that my adverse event/reaction is relatively rare, and the vaccines are largely safe and effective, but no medication is safe for everyone all of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The symptoms came on gradually after I had my second dose. The first symptom I remember is the worst migraine I’ve ever had. I remember sitting on the toilet (not doing anything too straining..), feeling as if my head was splitting in two. A few times my vision went almost entirely dark, as if the lights in the room were being dimmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My set of symptoms was roughly as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tingling&lt;/strong&gt;/paresthesia that went up the front of my throat, to the back of my head and ears&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My ears went beet-red on a few occasions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;blood pressure was swinging wildly&lt;/strong&gt;, anywhere from 120/80, normal for me, up to ~187/110, and down again.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;resting heartrate&lt;/strong&gt; (lying in bed) stayed above 120 bpm constantly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accompanying the heartrate at times were &lt;strong&gt;painful palpitations&lt;/strong&gt; (hard heartbeat with chest pain)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For months after the vaccination &lt;strong&gt;I couldn’t sleep more than 3 hours per night&lt;/strong&gt;, as evidenced during an in-hospital sleep test I had a few months later&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I had &lt;strong&gt;tremors&lt;/strong&gt; in my hands/my &lt;strong&gt;hands would shake&lt;/strong&gt; from nothing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I had periods of &lt;strong&gt;severe anxiety&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;agitation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perhaps worse than the anxiety were periods of &lt;strong&gt;extreme, unfounded anger&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;irritability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I developed roaring &lt;strong&gt;tinnitus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I consistently felt way too &lt;strong&gt;warm&lt;/strong&gt;, with some excessive &lt;strong&gt;sweating&lt;/strong&gt; and poor tolerance to heat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;muscles&lt;/strong&gt; felt &lt;strong&gt;weak&lt;/strong&gt; and I felt &lt;strong&gt;out of breath&lt;/strong&gt; with minimal exertion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I had some &lt;strong&gt;joint&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;muscle pain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dizziness&lt;/strong&gt; on standing, with fainting only happening once, but I still often bend down after standing up in order to prevent this from recurring&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nausea&lt;/strong&gt; without vomiting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some &lt;strong&gt;skin discolouration&lt;/strong&gt; appeared that hasn’t gone away (whitening), but it hasn’t gotten worse either&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Occasionally I would get some general skin itching&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My most debilitating symptom was and is, a &lt;strong&gt;complete and total inability to concentrate&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;think&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;make decisions&lt;/strong&gt;, rendering me largely incapable of taking care of myself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at data from my phone from around this time, all the photos are of blood pressure and heartrate measurements, or photos of my skin/ears. I felt alone in this, and I imagined doctors might not know much about my condition. I figured I’d need to look into this on my own, but I’d never been more poorly equipped to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brief context for the muscle weakness and breathlessness. I’m very much at my ideal weight and I don’t smoke or use drugs. Prior to VLH I used to do weightlifting 4 times per week. I could bench press 125kg (275lbs), but after the vaccination, if I tried to swim a lap in a 25 metre-long pool, I found I had to stop for a long time to catch my breath and let my heart calm down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect my thinking was not logical at all. My girlfriend had gone to London and I’d intended to fix up her car by the time she got back. I quickly lifted out of my job (I couldn’t think or focus at all), and all I did was focus on the car, with some intermittent lying in the grass when exhauzted. When I was home I tried to research my condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;work-relationship-and-disability&quot;&gt;Work, relationship, and disability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My life has changed in a variety of ways since this started and it’s been challenging for me to try to find the right words to explain my situation to friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always been a hard worker, and I derive a great deal of my self worth from my ability to think, work, and make money. If I tried to explain my current situation to my past self I’m not convinced that I would be very understanding. I think I would write-, a lot of what I have to say, off as laziness. ‘Why doesn’t he just do x and y, it only takes 5 minutes.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s because of this that I can’t resent anyone who doesn’t immediately understand and accept what I say when I try to explain my situation. My reality is so far from anything they are living and thus it must sound very foreign to them, as it would to myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my friends, family, my ex-girlfriend, I must appear to be fine. I look healthy. I can form sentences and say words. But I cannot function. I can’t get things done. Sending an email is too much for me most of the time. I spend the entirety of most of my days lying in bed, not doing anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast with my previous life, where I could not lie down to watch TV unless I’d been productive all day, and preferably not until after I’d worked out as well, this is clearly quite a drastic change, and nothing I would play around with doing without being forced to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My symptoms are hard to explain. At my worst I cannot read and comprehend paragraphs or sentences. I might go out to the store or pharmacy, and not be able to focus on anything. Asking for assistance seems like too much of an effort, so I would just go home and try another day. Nothing helps at this point except sleeping, but I’m never ‘all better’ after sleep. Just slightly less trashed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding people who are dealing with the same situation online has helped enormously, even if many of them often sound quite gloomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel inadequate in many ways. One of the things I feel bad about is how poorly I do with replying to friends and family. I’m often days or weeks late in responding to text messages. If I get an unplanned phone call I will ignore it. Partially because I know I will be asked how I’m doing, I know I will not be understood if I try to explain, and even if I were I spend so much of my own time thinking about how to solve my situation that I really don’t care to be forced to talk about it with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I find helps those who know me understand, is to remind them that they’d be hard-pressed to find anyone as ambitious as me. I really &lt;strong&gt;am&lt;/strong&gt; as sick as I say I am. I really cannot do the things I claim to not be able to do, for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of this, conversation often seems like too much cognitive load for me, so I find it best to avoid it and self-isolate. I don’t want any pity. All I would ask of anyone is to understand and accept that I am how I say, and then I would prefer to ignore it during conversations unless I explicitly bring it up. I would much rather distract my mind with something different than what I’m concerned with all day, every day. Every day of the week I read medical research papers, and I read chatrooms and talk to people in similar situations as me, when I have the energy to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhat luckily I am fascinated by these things so it isn’t as depressing as it sounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we go back to the beginning, the first thing I realised was lost was my job. I remember sitting at my desk at home, mid-covid/’lockdowns’ (so working from home was the norm). I would just stare at the screen and try to form thoughts, and feel like I couldn’t. I felt like I couldn’t conjure more than perhaps 2-3 thoughts per day. I couldn’t focus on the code I was writing. I should have informed the client, as well as my friend and coworker, about my situation, but I didn’t. It seemed too much for me at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I met up with my girlfriend at the time I was constantly having issues with anxiety and agitation. I would sometimes flood her with text messages where I wondered what might be wrong with me, and I found it hard to control. I remember complaining about not being able to think or make decisions too. She was great throughout this, as she always has been, but I didn’t know how to tackle the situation myself. I saw that how I felt was making her feel bad and suggested that we should meet-up less frequently, and message less, which in my mind was me protecting her mental health from being affected by what I was going through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went on a trip somewhere shortly after the first vaccination, which.. I actually managed to enjoy to a degree, so I must have gotten worse with time since then, but I still remember I had bouts of agitation (and perhaps depression) on that trip, as well as some joint pain which I didn’t attribute to this then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point she goes to London, I stay oddly focused on trying to fix up a car, and myself.. I find I have hyperthyroidism, have surgery, move abroad.. and we broke up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful that she didn’t have to sit and watch me go through all of this, and that she doesn’t have to see how I am today. And I’m very thankful for our time together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;anger-and-irritability&quot;&gt;Anger and irritability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I find interesting about this has been the unfounded anger I’ve felt since getting sick. I felt more anger than I’ve ever deal with in my life before that, over nothing in particular. I would think more violent thoughts, think ‘expletives’ at people I cared about, as well as strangers, and I got very careless about burning bridges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples of relationships potentially harmed (without making too many excuses for myself..), is with my mom’s family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mom and her siblings had a dispute over inheritance at the time, where I got involved and played a part in the disagreements. I would have preferred to have played a more diplomatic role in the issue.The issue is now ‘resolved’, but my mom and her brother, my uncle, whom we’ve always been close to, are no longer talking. The issue was a minor one. What adds insult to injury is that my uncle is terminally ill and there’s not endless time to make things right. My anger is a lot better today but my energy is not, and energy is needed to patch things up, much as it is needed with most things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example of irritability was, as I remember, one time when I went to a doctor’s appointment. The doctor suggested I see a cardiologist, a reasonable idea, and suggested that the ‘tingling’ I experienced could be from ‘muscle tension’, an idea I found so ridiculous that, after refusing the cardiologist referral, I said to him: ‘Simple solution for a simple man’, and stormed out. Thus burning a bridge with someone who could have been my ally in this. And doing/saying ‘just’ that took a great deal of restraint on my part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both my anger issues and agitation/anxiety are much improved today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;laboratory-tests-and-treatments&quot;&gt;Laboratory tests and treatments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll only skip over this part very briefly here. My intention is to go over this in detail in another post, for.. only the few who might potentially care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My laboratory tests were largely unremarkable, but they did eventually show overt hyperthyroidism, for which I had definitive treatment in the form of surgery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This improved much of my mood-related symptoms but cognition remained my biggest issue as it was before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hyperkalemia was detected on 3 occasions, and I’d noted an association between my symptoms and potassium intake. Improvement also noted with fludrocortisone (but a PRA/Aldosterone test was normal). Slightly alkaline urine test indicating possible compensation for acidosis. 
Lipids were consistently under the reference range, unspecific symptom and not a big concern, but aligns well with the hyperthyroidism diagnosis.
AM cortisol consistently low-normal (equivocal) with normal adrenal response to ACTH stimulation testing.
Autoimmune markers related to Lupus detected but not elevated. Clotting markers (late test) normal. 
Ferritin always low-normal. TPO antibodies slightly elevated (consistent with either autoimmune hypothyroidism or Graves/hyperthyroidism).
Adrenal cortex antibodies negative, in addition to the stimulation testing described above this makes primary adrenal insufficiency unlikely, even though low dose hydrocortisone definitely has a positive impact on my symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are fascinated by long haul at all, or dealing with it yourself, then perhaps stay tuned for the next post I &lt;em&gt;intend&lt;/em&gt; to write. It might be good, or at the very least interesting, to me.. But I’m not offering medical advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;focusing-on-recovery-moving-abroad&quot;&gt;Focusing on recovery, moving abroad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part doesn’t serve much of a purpose except to share an anecdote. 
After my surgery for hyperthyroidism I improved to an extent, particularly mood-related symptoms, but I realised soon that it wasn’t going to make me functional enough to be able to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to take a break and focus on recovering. It felt important to me to get out of my usual environment. If I stayed at home I would have been constantly reminded that I’m not participating in society like my friends and colleagues, and that I’m not with the girl I loved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I took off to London and decided to try living there for a while. To rest, eat, and exercise, with a change in scenery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This didn’t go all-too great initially. With my limited capacity for thinking/acting I spent much too long renting temporary (and expensive) places to stay at before I finally found a long-term place to rent. Small things like learning to use public transportation, the trains and the tube, were daunting tasks for me. I did manage it in the end and I’m happy I tried living there overall. I needed a distraction and I needed to rest and wait-and-see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did some exploring out there, went to some museums, climbing gyms, plenty of restaurants, tried running and weight lifting.. and generally learned much about my physical limitations. I also learned that the weather isn’t as bad as they say it is over there. It rarely seemed to rain and it wasn’t very windy. Apparently ‘windy’ to a Londoner means.. a single gust of wind every hour or so. Perhaps this says something about the country I’m from. However I did find that during winter the heating/insulation in the house(s) was not as good as what I’m used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon next-day delivery was very neat, and the variety of restaurants, although I tended to opt for the same ones to avoid any unnecessary cognitive load or decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shortly realised I wasn’t going to ‘power through’ the sickness with intense exercise. For weight lifting and running in particular it was apparent that they were making me worse, which is in alignment with what many people online have described.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy I tried this and I’m more content with being home now after this journey abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;current-symptoms-flare-ups-and-triggers&quot;&gt;Current symptoms, flare ups and triggers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My symptoms today are broadly similar to what they were, although with the following changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The tinnitus is gone, unless I’m currently going through a flare up, this applies to most of the other symptoms that are gone as well&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The extreme agitation, anxiety, and anger, is largely gone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m now sleeping much longer than I was&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m still not exercising, although I wish I was&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m still not able to think/concentrate/work, this has always been my most troubling symptom&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I still spend most of my days in bed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tachycardia/high heart rate and palpitations are largely gone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blood pressure is not swining like it was&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what is involved in a flare up of symptoms? Are there clear and definite triggers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few ways in which I can reliably make my symptoms worse. I’m aware that exercise is common for mostly everyone with vaccine long haul. I don’t believe everyone has experimented with the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I do &lt;em&gt;intense exercise&lt;/em&gt;, such as &lt;strong&gt;weighlifting&lt;/strong&gt;, my symptoms flare up as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I get intense &lt;strong&gt;pressure&lt;/strong&gt;/heat inside of my face/&lt;strong&gt;head&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My body, &lt;strong&gt;limbs&lt;/strong&gt;, hands and feet in particular, &lt;strong&gt;go ice-cold&lt;/strong&gt; and stay that way for hours&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;tinnitus&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;sent roaring&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;shortness of breath&lt;/strong&gt; is exacerbated, with no exertion necessary&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;thinking&lt;/strong&gt; becomes &lt;strong&gt;confused&lt;/strong&gt;, I &lt;strong&gt;can’t focus, read, or write&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;mood&lt;/strong&gt; plummets and I get &lt;strong&gt;irritability and/or depression&lt;/strong&gt; like I did in the beginning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;muscles tense up&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;recovery time&lt;/strong&gt; from a flare up, for the confusion in particular &lt;strong&gt;takes several days&lt;/strong&gt;, and that’s just to get to the already-subpar baseline level of functioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I experience similar symptoms after:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eating &lt;strong&gt;sugar&lt;/strong&gt;, this sounds to my prejudiced self as if I just buy into anyone pushing a no-sugar/plant-based diet, but I don’t. Sugar makes my symptoms flare up for some reason. Not as intensely as exercise would but enough for me to avoid chocolate for the first time in my life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;ADHD medication&lt;/strong&gt;, which helped me prior to the vaccination, now helps for about an hour before triggering a flare-up exactly as described above. This has meant that I’ve avoided this medicine since the beginning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;life-today-hope-and-future-prospects&quot;&gt;Life today, hope and future prospects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So.. where am I now. What’s on the agenda, and is there any hope for the future? (my future that is, the only one that matters :p)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As described above I’m still not capable of working. I’m still not doing well by the people I care about, I’m not able to take good care of myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m starting rehab and financial assistance as I go through that. In the past I always thought I’d rather kill myself than accept disability benefits. I could think of nothing worse than ‘being a loser’, to be someone who is not contributing to society in any meaningful way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also believe, if I’m honest with myself, that I used to think people who went on disability were lazy. But I now realise that there is something wrong with these people, generally speaking. No one &lt;strong&gt;wants&lt;/strong&gt; to not contribute. No one wants to just sit at home and do nothing, to be an outlier in society. The people who don’t judge you for not working will likely still pity you on some level. You do not have a journey in common with your peers, and it is not popular with the opposite sex. It won’t do your self confidence any good. Realising this has greatly changed my perspective towards people on disability. And more generally, the apparent effect on anger and agitation has given me a different perspective towards moody people. Although I wouldn’t excuse them or seek out their company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still unwilling to accept permanent disability benefits for myself, but I am willing to take it while I see whether I can get better. And there are signs that I might be able to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 10 months of feeling like a &lt;strong&gt;stroke&lt;/strong&gt; sufferer, a complete vegetable, who &lt;strong&gt;cannot sit upright&lt;/strong&gt; for more than 10 minutes without becoming exhausted, I’ve had a few days where I would say I was completely productive, as much as I ever was before getting sick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;strong&gt;huge deal&lt;/strong&gt; for me. I have wondered time and again whether my brain is simply gone, due to injury or damage of some sort, and seeing that it isn’t, that it can be mitigated to such an extent, provides a glimmer of hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say this tentatively because I can only be productive with the assistance of medications, and I feel so drained after those days that I only do it when I know I &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; get something done. Regardless, I couldn’t do this before because I couldn’t tolerate the medication involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing this post on its own is something that has been unthinkable for me since this whole thing started. Now, not only have I written it, I also wrote the software/website behind it, taking great care to make it as easily readable as possible, and to structure the content so that people might find it useful and not too much of a strain to read. I did not think I would necessarily ever write software again, no matter how simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With any luck I will continue to improve, hopefully to a place where I can at least be productive and content with myself. If I can work and create things I’m happy, if not I’m miserable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next section I’m going to briefly describe long haul in general. What it is, the effect of the vaccines, some interesting studies and polls, and other peoples experiences. In a future post, that I expect no one except &lt;strong&gt;long haulers or huge medical nerds&lt;/strong&gt; will read, I intend to go into how I’ve finally managed to have some days of what I would describe as ‘complete recovery’, albeit with the limitations I briefly touched on above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-covid--and-vaccine-long-haul&quot;&gt;2. Covid- and vaccine long haul&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Pellentesque a velit convallis, egestas erat sed, placerat nulla. Sed placerat rutrum ante, eget cursus dui molestie sed. Proin lobortis in ante vel accumsan. Etiam aliquam dictum metus, eleifend euismod quam semper eget. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia curae; Nulla metus elit, tempus id neque at, imperdiet pellentesque sapien. Curabitur tincidunt ac metus et cursus. Suspendisse sagittis malesuada tortor, ac accumsan tortor luctus sit amet. Nullam nulla urna, malesuada a iaculis vitae, rutrum nec eros. Cras maximus efficitur aliquet. Suspendisse velit lectus, lobortis et purus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the terminology used below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CLH&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;Covid long hauler&lt;/strong&gt;. Someone who has been infected with covid-19 and has been dealing with ongoing symptoms for at least 12 weeks beyond the acute phase of the infection. [TODO: https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng188/chapter/Recommendations] Also known as &lt;strong&gt;PASC&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VLH&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;Vaccine long hauler&lt;/strong&gt;. Someone who has been vaccinated with one of the covid-19 vaccines, who deals with persistent symptoms near-identical to those of the average covid long hauler.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ME/CFS&lt;/strong&gt;: Myalgic encephalomyelitis/&lt;strong&gt;chronic fatigue syndrome&lt;/strong&gt;. Mildly related to the topic at hand, often connected to post-viral illness.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;clh-symptoms&quot;&gt;CLH symptoms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrast with my own symptoms. VLH symptoms in general. 
Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Pellentesque a velit convallis, egestas erat sed, placerat nulla. Sed placerat rutrum ante, eget cursus dui molestie sed. Proin lobortis in ante vel accumsan. Etiam aliquam dictum metus, eleifend euismod quam semper eget. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia curae; Nulla metus elit, tempus id neque at, imperdiet pellentesque sapien. Curabitur tincidunt ac metus et cursus. Suspendisse sagittis malesuada tortor, ac accumsan tortor luctus sit amet. Nullam nulla urna, malesuada a iaculis vitae, rutrum nec eros. Cras maximus efficitur aliquet. Suspendisse velit lectus, lobortis et purus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-similarities-between-clh-and-vlh&quot;&gt;Other similarities between CLH and VLH&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Pellentesque a velit convallis, egestas erat sed, placerat nulla. Sed placerat rutrum ante, eget cursus dui molestie sed. Proin lobortis in ante vel accumsan. Etiam aliquam dictum metus, eleifend euismod quam semper eget. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia curae; Nulla metus elit, tempus id neque at, imperdiet pellentesque sapien. Curabitur tincidunt ac metus et cursus. Suspendisse sagittis malesuada tortor, ac accumsan tortor luctus sit amet. Nullam nulla urna, malesuada a iaculis vitae, rutrum nec eros. Cras maximus efficitur aliquet. Suspendisse velit lectus, lobortis et purus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deteroriation-of-clh-with-vaccination&quot;&gt;Deteroriation of CLH with vaccination&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Pellentesque a velit convallis, egestas erat sed, placerat nulla. Sed placerat rutrum ante, eget cursus dui molestie sed. Proin lobortis in ante vel accumsan. Etiam aliquam dictum metus, eleifend euismod quam semper eget. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia curae; Nulla metus elit, tempus id neque at, imperdiet pellentesque sapien. Curabitur tincidunt ac metus et cursus. Suspendisse sagittis malesuada tortor, ac accumsan tortor luctus sit amet. Nullam nulla urna, malesuada a iaculis vitae, rutrum nec eros. Cras maximus efficitur aliquet. Suspendisse velit lectus, lobortis et purus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;studies&quot;&gt;Studies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/jmv.27689&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-7-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;. The people with the &lt;strong&gt;highest antibody response post-vaccination&lt;/strong&gt; were the ones who &lt;strong&gt;developed worse symptoms&lt;/strong&gt;, perhaps indicating an excessive immune response in this group. Various UK studies show &lt;strong&gt;up to 31% of long covid patients developing worse symptoms after vaccination&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ukhsa.koha-ptfs.co.uk/cgi-bin/koha/opac-retrieve-file.pl?id=fe4f10cd3cd509fe045ad4f72ae0dfff&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-8-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;community-polls-and-surveys&quot;&gt;Community polls and surveys&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Pellentesque a velit convallis, egestas erat sed, placerat nulla. Sed placerat rutrum ante, eget cursus dui molestie sed. Proin lobortis in ante vel accumsan. Etiam aliquam dictum metus, eleifend euismod quam semper eget. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia curae; Nulla metus elit, tempus id neque at, imperdiet pellentesque sapien. Curabitur tincidunt ac metus et cursus. Suspendisse sagittis malesuada tortor, ac accumsan tortor luctus sit amet. Nullam nulla urna, malesuada a iaculis vitae, rutrum nec eros. Cras maximus efficitur aliquet. Suspendisse velit lectus, lobortis et purus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;increased-rate-of-hospitalisation-after-vaccination-of-patients-with-prior-covid-infection&quot;&gt;Increased rate of hospitalisation after vaccination of patients with prior covid infection&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Pellentesque a velit convallis, egestas erat sed, placerat nulla. Sed placerat rutrum ante, eget cursus dui molestie sed. Proin lobortis in ante vel accumsan. Etiam aliquam dictum metus, eleifend euismod quam semper eget. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia curae; Nulla metus elit, tempus id neque at, imperdiet pellentesque sapien. Curabitur tincidunt ac metus et cursus. Suspendisse sagittis malesuada tortor, ac accumsan tortor luctus sit amet. Nullam nulla urna, malesuada a iaculis vitae, rutrum nec eros. Cras maximus efficitur aliquet. Suspendisse velit lectus, lobortis et purus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-peoples-lives-are-impacted-by-the-symptoms-of-clh-and-vlh&quot;&gt;How peoples lives are impacted by the symptoms of CLH and VLH&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Pellentesque a velit convallis, egestas erat sed, placerat nulla. Sed placerat rutrum ante, eget cursus dui molestie sed. Proin lobortis in ante vel accumsan. Etiam aliquam dictum metus, eleifend euismod quam semper eget. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia curae; Nulla metus elit, tempus id neque at, imperdiet pellentesque sapien. Curabitur tincidunt ac metus et cursus. Suspendisse sagittis malesuada tortor, ac accumsan tortor luctus sit amet. Nullam nulla urna, malesuada a iaculis vitae, rutrum nec eros. Cras maximus efficitur aliquet. Suspendisse velit lectus, lobortis et purus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Pellentesque a velit convallis, egestas erat sed, placerat nulla. Sed placerat rutrum ante, eget cursus dui molestie sed. Proin lobortis in ante vel accumsan. Etiam aliquam dictum metus, eleifend euismod quam semper eget. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia curae; Nulla metus elit, tempus id neque at, imperdiet pellentesque sapien. Curabitur tincidunt ac metus et cursus. Suspendisse sagittis malesuada tortor, ac accumsan tortor luctus sit amet. Nullam nulla urna, malesuada a iaculis vitae, rutrum nec eros. Cras maximus efficitur aliquet. Suspendisse velit lectus, lobortis et purus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#how-peoples-lives-are-impacted-by-the-symptoms-of-CLH-and-VLH&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#conclusion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ref-list&quot;&gt;

  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-1-title&quot;&gt;Hyperkalemia (High Potassium): Symptoms, Causes, Treatment. Accessed April 7, 2022. https://www.healthline.com/health/high-potassium-hyperkalemia#symptoms&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-2-title&quot;&gt;Metabolic Alkalosis | American Society of Nephrology. Accessed April 7, 2022. https://jasn.asnjournals.org/content/11/2/369&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-3-title&quot;&gt;Cortisol - Clinical Biochemistry. Accessed April 7, 2022. https://www.ouh.nhs.uk/biochemistry/tests/tests-catalogue/cortisol.aspx&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-4-title&quot;&gt;Expert says some chronic fatigue syndrome sufferers should be exempt from Covid-19 vaccination | RNZ News. Accessed April 7, 2022. https://www.rnz.co.nz/news/national/456598/expert-says-some-chronic-fatigue-syndrome-sufferers-should-be-exempt-from-covid-19-vaccination&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-5-title&quot;&gt;https://reddit.com/r/vaccinelonghaulers&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-6-title&quot;&gt;https://reddit.com/r/covidlonghaulers&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-7-title&quot;&gt;Relationship between changes in symptoms and antibody titers after a single vaccination in patients with Long COVID - Tsuchida - Journal of Medical Virology - Wiley Online Library. Accessed April 7, 2022. https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/jmv.27689&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-8-title&quot;&gt;Details for: The effectiveness of vaccination against long COVID: A rapid evidence briefing › UK Health Security Agency catalogue. Accessed April 7, 2022. https://ukhsa.koha-ptfs.co.uk/cgi-bin/koha/opac-detail.pl?biblionumber=64359&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-9-title&quot;&gt;So… am I the only one NOT feeling better after the vaccine? : covidlonghaulers. Accessed April 7, 2022. https://www.reddit.com/r/covidlonghaulers/comments/nk05qh/so_am_i_the_only_one_not_feeling_better_after_the/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-10-title&quot;&gt;The vaccine made me worse!!!! : covidlonghaulers. Accessed April 7, 2022. https://www.reddit.com/r/covidlonghaulers/comments/thdoia/the_vaccine_made_me_worse/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-11-title&quot;&gt;Li LL, Zheng C, La J, et al. Impact of prior SARS-CoV-2 infection on incidence of hospitalization and adverse events following mRNA SARS-CoV-2 vaccination: A nationwide, retrospective cohort study. Vaccine. 2022;40(8):1082-1089. doi:10.1016/j.vaccine.2022.01.026&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-12-title&quot;&gt;CDC says waiting longer between Pfizer, Moderna doses may reduce myocarditis risk. Accessed April 7, 2022. https://www.cnbc.com/amp/2022/02/23/cdc-says-waiting-longer-between-pfizer-moderna-doses-may-reduce-myocarditis-risk.html&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-13-title&quot;&gt;Post-COVID Conditions | CDC. Accessed April 7, 2022. https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/long-term-effects/index.html&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-14-title&quot;&gt;Nuovo GJ, Magro C, Shaffer T, et al. Endothelial cell damage is the central part of COVID-19 and a mouse model induced by injection of the S1 subunit of the spike protein. Ann Diagn Pathol. 2021;51:151682. doi:10.1016/j.anndiagpath.2020.151682
 TODO: Add studies here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-15-title&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SobqUw7gqhs = Vaccine long hauler, healthcare worker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-16-title&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H7inaTiDKaU - Vaccine long hauler, cyclist&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;hidden&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h1 id=&quot;relevant-quotes-from-each-citation&quot;&gt;Relevant quotes from each citation&lt;/h1&gt;

  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;blockquote class=&quot;citation-1-highlights&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;“The symptoms of high potassium depend on the level of the mineral in your blood. […] if your potassium levels are high enough to cause symptoms, you &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; have: &lt;strong&gt;tiredness&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;weakness&lt;/strong&gt;, a feeling of &lt;strong&gt;numbness&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;tingling&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;nausea&lt;/strong&gt;,
&lt;strong&gt;trouble breathing&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;chest pain&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;palpitations&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;blockquote class=&quot;citation-2-highlights&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;Dietary potassium depletion&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;associated with modest metabolic alkalosis&lt;/strong&gt; and with an &lt;strong&gt;increase in intracellular sodium&lt;/strong&gt; and proton concentrations and suppression of aldosterone (27,28). Metabolic alkalosis is generated primarily by an intracellular shift of protons. However, potassium depletion is also associated with enhanced renal ammonia production, and a contribution of increased net acid excretion has not been excluded in humans (29,30). Similarly, &lt;strong&gt;administration of aldosterone causes only a slight degree of metabolic alkalosis if potassium depletion is prevented&lt;/strong&gt; (31)”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;blockquote class=&quot;citation-3-highlights&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;“In adult patients who are not on steroid treatment, 9 a.m. cortisol &amp;lt;100 nmol/L suggests adrenal insufficiency, &lt;strong&gt;9 a.m. cortisol &amp;gt;400 nmol/L makes adrenal insufficiency unlikely&lt;/strong&gt;, - For 9 a.m. cortisol of &lt;strong&gt;100-400, consider a short synacthen test&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;blockquote class=&quot;citation-4-highlights&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;“Expert &lt;strong&gt;says some chronic fatigue syndrome sufferers should be exempt from Covid-19 vaccination&lt;/strong&gt; “&lt;strong&gt;University of Otago’s Emeritus Professor Warren Tate&lt;/strong&gt; says he is aware of serious reactions triggered by the Pfizer vaccine in several people who have the condition. He believes some of those with the disease &lt;strong&gt;shouldn’t be expected to be vaccinated&lt;/strong&gt;.” Preliminary findings of a &lt;strong&gt;survey of ME/CFS sufferers and those with Long Covid&lt;/strong&gt;, carried out by the &lt;strong&gt;Associated New Zealand ME Society&lt;/strong&gt; (ANZMES), found &lt;strong&gt;nearly 20 percent of the 359 survey participants had experienced a relapse, with worsened symptoms that had not returned to baseline, after taking the Pfizer vaccine&lt;/strong&gt;. The findings will be submitted to the Immunisation Advisory Centre (Imac) and the Ministry. Tate has also submitted data to Imac over his concerns.”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-5-highlights&quot;&gt;Reddit’s vaccine long hauler community: &lt;a href=&quot;https://reddit.com/r/vaccinelonghaulers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://reddit.com/r/vaccinelonghaulers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;citation-6-highlights&quot;&gt;Reddit’s covid long hauler community: &lt;a href=&quot;https://reddit.com/r/covidlonghaulers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://reddit.com/r/covidlonghaulers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;blockquote class=&quot;citation-7-highlights&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;“Relationship between changes in &lt;strong&gt;symptoms&lt;/strong&gt; and antibody titers after a &lt;strong&gt;single vaccination&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;patients with Long COVID&lt;/strong&gt; This study evaluated &lt;strong&gt;post-vaccination changes in symptoms&lt;/strong&gt; and antibody titers &lt;strong&gt;in patients with Long COVID&lt;/strong&gt;. Patients visiting the outpatient department specializing in Long COVID at our hospital were enrolled. Changes in &lt;strong&gt;symptoms&lt;/strong&gt; were &lt;strong&gt;evaluated before&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;14–21 days after&lt;/strong&gt; first &lt;strong&gt;vaccination&lt;/strong&gt;. Antibody titers were measured using ARCHITECT SARS-CoV-2 IgG II Quant at the same time. This study included &lt;strong&gt;42 patients&lt;/strong&gt; […] &lt;strong&gt;Post-vaccination symptoms&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;fatigue, joint pain&lt;/strong&gt;, and taste and olfactory abnormalities) were &lt;strong&gt;relieved&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;worsened&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;unchanged&lt;/strong&gt; in 7 (&lt;strong&gt;16.7%&lt;/strong&gt;), 9 (&lt;strong&gt;21.4%&lt;/strong&gt;), and 26 (&lt;strong&gt;61.9%&lt;/strong&gt;) patients, respectively. Ratios of pre- and post-vaccination antibody titers were 53, 40, and 174 in the unchanged, relief, and worsened groups, respectively. &lt;strong&gt;The worsened group had the significantly highest antibody titer ratio&lt;/strong&gt; (p = 0.02). The higher increased rate of the antibody titer in the worsened group than in the non-worsened group suggests an &lt;strong&gt;excessive immune response to vaccination associated with worsening of sequelae&lt;/strong&gt;. Although patients with Long COVID should be vaccinated, additional concerns should be addressed.”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;blockquote class=&quot;citation-8-highlights&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;“An online survey by Scherlinger et al […] asked Frenchspeaking adults with post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC, persistent symptoms lasting &amp;gt;4 weeks after probable or confirmed COVID-19 infection and no alternative diagnosis to explain the symptoms) whether their symptoms improved or worsened following vaccination
(Pfizer [78%], Moderna [16%], AstraZeneca [4%]) (20). The survey was completed by &lt;strong&gt;567 respondents&lt;/strong&gt; (median age 44 years, 83% women) in August 2021, 64% of participants had a confirmed COVID-19 infection, 25% had one vaccine dose and 45% had 2 vaccine doses. Symptoms of PASC included fever or chills, fatigue, brain fog, headaches, changing mood or impact on morale, sleeping issues, costal pain, dyspnoea, cough, palpitations, muscle aches, joint pain, paraesthesia or tingling, anosmia or ageusia, diarrhoea or vomiting, spontaneous bruises, and pruritus. • Of the 380 participants who reported long COVID at the time of vaccination, 117
&lt;strong&gt;(31%) reported a global worsening of symptoms&lt;/strong&gt; (including fever/chills [74%],
&lt;strong&gt;gastrointestinal&lt;/strong&gt; symptoms [70%], &lt;strong&gt;paraesthesia&lt;/strong&gt; [64%] and &lt;strong&gt;arthralgia&lt;/strong&gt; [63%]),
whereas 83 (21.8%) reported a global improvement in symptoms (including
anosmia [62%] and brain fog [51%]), and 179 (47%) reported no change in
symptoms following vaccination.
[…]
&lt;strong&gt;There was little evidence of differences in results between vaccine types (p=0.60)&lt;/strong&gt;
[…]
[Another UK survey specified showed 23.2% improved vs. 15.4% worse]”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;blockquote class=&quot;citation-9-highlights&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;“[…]I’m extremely glad for those who improved. I got Pfizer though and &lt;strong&gt;both doses made me much worse&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;I wasn’t cured by any means pre-vax but I was feeling pretty clear-headed and energetic.&lt;/strong&gt; Now &lt;strong&gt;my brain fog is&lt;/strong&gt; [some of] &lt;strong&gt;the worst it’s been&lt;/strong&gt;—highly nauseous and had &lt;strong&gt;trouble thinking all day yesterday&lt;/strong&gt;.” // “I recently got Pfizer too (one dose) and I went through a relapse soon after receiving it. &lt;strong&gt;It brought back the excruciating pain from early last year&lt;/strong&gt; (LH since March 2020).” //  “I’ve only had my first dose but it actually &lt;strong&gt;set me back a lot&lt;/strong&gt;…&lt;strong&gt;I feel like I’m right back to being a few weeks post covid&lt;/strong&gt; when I had been slowly getting a bit better.” //  “&lt;strong&gt;Both vaccines absolutely trashed me&lt;/strong&gt;. Still trying to recover from the second one.”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;blockquote class=&quot;citation-10-highlights&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;“I had the second Phizer shot on December 5th. 3 weeks later [the paramedics] were at my house because my &lt;strong&gt;heart rate was 204&lt;/strong&gt;. Ever since then I have had &lt;strong&gt;head pressure and dizziness, heart palpitations&lt;/strong&gt; and now I’m getting &lt;strong&gt;pins and needles&lt;/strong&gt; in my legs when I’m laying down… I was already a covid longhauler… I was actually feeling somewhat better[…]&lt;strong&gt;3 months out from vaccine and still in bad shape&lt;/strong&gt; […] &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; actually &lt;strong&gt;feel worse from the shot than I did longhauling from Covid&lt;/strong&gt;.” // “Same.” // “Yup, same here. &lt;strong&gt;My long haul was almost nonexistent previous to vax and after it’s worse than my actual covid long haul ever was. By like 100.&lt;/strong&gt; And I didn’t even get the 2nd dose”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;blockquote class=&quot;citation-11-highlights&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;In previously-infected patients, the hospitalization rate increased above baseline&lt;/strong&gt; one day &lt;strong&gt;following vaccination&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;158.2&lt;/strong&gt;/100,000 after dose 2 versus &lt;strong&gt;57.3&lt;/strong&gt;/100,000 pre-dose, p &amp;lt; 0.001)”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;blockquote class=&quot;citation-12-highlights&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;[According to the CDC, waiting longer between mRNA doses may reduce the risk of myocarditis]&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;blockquote class=&quot;citation-13-highlights&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;“Difficulty breathing or &lt;strong&gt;shortness of breath&lt;/strong&gt;,&lt;strong&gt;tiredness&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;fatigue&lt;/strong&gt;,&lt;strong&gt;Symptoms&lt;/strong&gt; that get &lt;strong&gt;worse after&lt;/strong&gt; physical or mental &lt;strong&gt;activities&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Difficulty thinking or concentrating&lt;/strong&gt; (sometimes referred to as “&lt;strong&gt;brain fog&lt;/strong&gt;”), Cough, &lt;strong&gt;Chest&lt;/strong&gt; or stomach &lt;strong&gt;pain&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Headache&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Fast-beating or pounding heart&lt;/strong&gt; (also known as &lt;strong&gt;heart palpitations&lt;/strong&gt;), &lt;strong&gt;Joint&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;muscle pain&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Pins-and-needles&lt;/strong&gt; feeling, Diarrhea, &lt;strong&gt;Sleep problems&lt;/strong&gt;, Fever, &lt;strong&gt;Dizziness on standing&lt;/strong&gt; (lightheadedness), Rash, &lt;strong&gt;Mood changes&lt;/strong&gt;, Change in smell or taste, Changes in menstrual period cycles”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;blockquote class=&quot;citation-14-highlights&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;Endothelial cell damage&lt;/strong&gt; is the central part of COVID-19 and a mouse model induced by injection of the S1 subunit of the spike protein […] The &lt;strong&gt;S1 subunit localized to the endothelia of microvessels in the mice brain&lt;/strong&gt; and showed co-localization with caspase-3, &lt;strong&gt;ACE2, IL6, TNFα&lt;/strong&gt;, and C5b-9. The surrounding neurons showed increased neuronal NOS and decreased MFSD2a. It is concluded that &lt;strong&gt;ACE2+ endothelial damage is a central part of SARS-CoV2 pathology and may be induced by the spike protein alone&lt;/strong&gt;. Thus, the diagnostic pathologist can use either hematoxylin and eosin stain or immunohistochemistry for caspase 3 and ACE2 to document the endothelial cell damage of COVID-19.”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;iframe id=&quot;vlh-1&quot; class=&quot;citation-15-highlights&quot; width=&quot;auto&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SobqUw7gqhs&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;iframe id=&quot;vlh-2&quot; class=&quot;citation-16-highlights&quot; width=&quot;auto&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/H7inaTiDKaU&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;modal fade&quot; id=&quot;citation-modal&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot; role=&quot;dialog&quot; aria-labelledby=&quot;citation-modal-label&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;modal-dialog&quot; role=&quot;document&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;modal-content&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;modal-header&quot;&gt;
        &lt;button type=&quot;button&quot; class=&quot;close&quot; data-dismiss=&quot;modal&quot; aria-label=&quot;Close&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&amp;times;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;modal-title&quot; id=&quot;citation-modal-label&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 12px;&quot;&gt;Some title&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;modal-body&quot;&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;modal-footer&quot;&gt;
        &lt;button type=&quot;button&quot; class=&quot;btn btn-default&quot; data-dismiss=&quot;modal&quot;&gt;Close&lt;/button&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    window.addEventListener(&quot;load&quot;, function() {

        var $spy = $('body').scrollspy({ target: '#sidebar-scrollspy', offset:82 });

        // $(window).on('scroll', function() {
        //     $(&quot;a&quot;).each(function() {
        //         if ( isScrolledIntoView($(this)) &amp;&amp; !$(this).hasClass('attention') &amp;&amp; !$(this).hasClass('animation-finished')) {
        //             $(this).addClass(&quot;attention&quot;);
        //             $(this)[0].addEventListener(&quot;animationend&quot;, function(e) {
        //                 console.log('Animationi ended kid');
        //                 console.log(e);
        //                 var $elem = $(e.target);
        //                 $elem.addClass(&quot;animation-finished&quot;);
        //                 $elem.removeClass(&quot;attention&quot;);
        //             });
        //         }
        //     });
        // });

        function isScrolledIntoView(elem) {
            var docViewTop = $(window).scrollTop();
            var docViewBottom = docViewTop + $(window).height();

            var elemTop = $(elem).offset().top;
            var elemBottom = elemTop + $(elem).height();

            return ((elemBottom &lt;= docViewBottom) &amp;&amp; (elemTop &gt;= docViewTop));
        }


        $('.trigger-modal').on('click', function(e) {
            e.preventDefault();
            var citationHighlightSelector = $(this).attr('data-targ');
            console.log('Citation highlight selector: ');
            console.log(citationHighlightSelector);
            var citationTitleSelector = citationHighlightSelector.replace('highlights', 'title');
            $modalBody = $(citationHighlightSelector);

            var hasTitle = $(citationTitleSelector) &amp;&amp; $(citationTitleSelector).length;
            var citationTitle = &quot;&quot;; 
            
            if (hasTitle) {
                citationTitle = $(citationTitleSelector).text();
            }

            $(&quot;#citation-modal&quot;).find(&quot;.modal-title&quot;).text(citationTitle);

            if ($modalBody &amp;&amp; $modalBody.length) {
                if ($($modalBody[0]).prop('tagName') !== 'IFRAME') {
                    $(&quot;#citation-modal&quot;).find(&quot;.modal-body&quot;).html($modalBody.html());
                } else {
                    var $currBody = $(&quot;#citation-modal&quot;).find(&quot;.modal-body&quot;);
                    $currBody.html('');
                    $($modalBody[0]).clone().appendTo($currBody);
                }
            }
            $('#citation-modal').modal('toggle');   
        });

        $('#citation-modal').on('hidden.bs.modal', function () {
            $(&quot;#citation-modal&quot;).find(&quot;.modal-body&quot;).html(''); 
        });

        $('#sidebar-scrollspy').on('activate.bs.scrollspy', function (e) {
            $(&quot;li:not(.active) ul.nav&quot;).css('display', 'none');
            $(&quot;li.active ul.nav&quot;).css('display', 'block');

            var currentScrollSpyText = &quot;&quot;;
            var $activeTopLi = $('#sidebar-scrollspy&gt;ul&gt;li.active');
            if ($activeTopLi &amp;&amp; $activeTopLi.length) {
                var currentScrollSpyText = $activeTopLi.find('a:first').text();
                var $activeSecondLi = $activeTopLi.find('li.active:first');
                if ($activeSecondLi &amp;&amp; $activeSecondLi.length) {
                    currentScrollSpyText += ': ' + $activeSecondLi.find('a:first').text();
                }
            }

            $(&quot;#mobile-scrollspy-status-bar span&quot;).text(currentScrollSpyText);
        });

        $(document).on('click','body *',function(e){
            if (!$(this) || !$(this).length || !$(this).attr('id') || !$(this).attr('id').startsWith('mobile-scrollspy-status-bar')) { // If it isn't, we will.. shut it down if it's expanded
                var $scrollSpyExpandedMobile = $('#sidebar-scrollspy.expanded');
                if ($scrollSpyExpandedMobile &amp;&amp; $scrollSpyExpandedMobile.length) {
                    $scrollSpyExpandedMobile.removeClass('expanded');
                }
                return true;
            } else { // If it's the mobile-scrollspy-status-bar
               e.preventDefault();
               e.stopPropagation();
               $(&quot;#sidebar-scrollspy&quot;).addClass('expanded');
               return false; // Equivalent to the above
            }
        });

        var offset = 80;

        $('#sidebar-scrollspy li a').on('click', function(event) {
            event.preventDefault();
            // $($(this).attr('href'))[0].scrollIntoView();
            $('html, body').animate({
                scrollTop: $($(this).attr('href')).offset().top - 80
            }, 1000);

            // scrollBy(0, -offset);
        });
    });
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;mobile-scrollspy-status-bar&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;vertical-alignment-container&quot;&gt;
        &lt;span&gt;1. Intro&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;nav id=&quot;sidebar-scrollspy&quot; class=&quot;sidebar-scrollspy bs-docs-sidebar affix&quot;&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;nav bs-docs-sidenav&quot;&gt;

&lt;li class=&quot;active&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;#my-experience-with-debilitating-illness-long-haul-and-potential-treatments&quot; id=&quot;part-1-link&quot;&gt;1. Intro&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;nav&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#my-own-story&quot;&gt;My own story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#onset-of-illness-and-symptom-progression&quot;&gt;Onset and progression of symptoms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#work-relationship-and-disability&quot;&gt;Work, relationship, disability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#anger-and-irritability&quot;&gt;Anger and irritability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;!-- Quit job, irritability, agitation, anxiety, break and break up  --&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#laboratory-tests-and-treatments&quot;&gt;Lab. tests and treatments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#focusing-on-recovery-moving-abroad&quot;&gt;Recovery, moving abroad&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#current-symptoms-flare-ups-and-triggers&quot;&gt;Current symptoms, flare ups, triggers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#life-today-hope-and-future-prospects&quot;&gt;Positivity and future prospects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;#2-covid--and-vaccine-long-haul&quot; id=&quot;part-2-link&quot;&gt;2. Long haul: Covid and vaccine&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;nav&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#clh-symptoms&quot;&gt;CLH symptoms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#other-similarities-between-clh-and-vlh&quot;&gt;Similarities between CLH and VLH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#deteroriation-of-clh-with-vaccination&quot;&gt;Deterioration of CLH with vaccination&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#studies&quot;&gt;Studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#community-polls-and-surveys&quot;&gt;Community polls and surveys&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#increased-rate-of-hospitalisation-after-vaccination-of-patients-with-prior-covid-infection&quot;&gt;Increased rate of hospitalisation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
    
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/nav&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;hidden&quot;&gt;
## TODOS:

- Create a photo showing symptoms by body part/system

After putting temporary subheadings in my post I realise it's all over the place. I think it would be neater if I organise it so that:
--my whole backstory and progression of symptoms comes first, the impact on my life as a whole,  followed by a description of VLH, its general set of symptoms and similarities with CLH,  the role of the vaccine in the context of CLH.. and then.. the.. meaning of these symptoms on peoples lives in general as evidenced by facebook and reddit posts.. would.. make it kind of neat and succinct. I think. 

My personal blood/urine tests and treatments could be an entirely separate post, seeing as it's of interest to almost no one. As well as ideas for treatment targets and what has worked for me. 

Proposed ToC:
* Backstory
 - What was I working with
 - What about previous fatigue 
 - Relationship with my ex 
 - What am I dealing with (without going into detail)
 - Onset of symptoms
 - Progression of symptoms
 - Last trip/working on the car and so on 
 - Current set of symptoms 
 - Disability and perspective 
 - Hope for the future. 
 - Point towards post 2 and/or more details on LH. 
* Covid- and vaccine LH 
 - CLH set of symptoms roughly
 - Brief description of VLH
 - Similarities between the two (same symptoms)
 - CLH worsening after vaccination common
 - Increased hospitalisation with prior covid infection 
 - Impact on peoples lives as evidenced by fb and reddit posts 
 - Conclusion
   -- started writing this without a clear end goal in mind. 

## A brief backstory 

I want to state here in the beginning that although I will start this post with bleak descriptions and pessimism (or realism), I will end it with some tentative optimism.

In summer 2021 I was running my own company with two of my friends, where I was working as a software consultant and developer. I was my own boss, I had a great girlfriend, and my company's biggest client (a sizeable Nordic hardware store chain) was impressed with the work we were doing for them, with VPs from abroad having shown interest in the software we were developing.

Today (*6 April 2022*), I'm ~ten months into disabling illness. I'm not working, no longer with my girlfriend, not exercising, and nowhere close to being functional as a person. Before this I had been dealing with some fatigue, but was doing really well with ADHD treatment.

## Covid- and vaccine long haul

### Same set of symptoms
The illness I'm struggling with is a form of PASC/Long Covid. As many now know, covid can cause long-lasting problems in susceptible individuals. In some cases, the present result is disability. It's less widely appreciated that the covid vaccines themselves appear to cause a similar syndrome for some. The set of symptoms described in both disorders is near-identical. 

### A significant proportion of covid long haulers get worse symptoms following covid vaccination

Both have support groups on facebook, and communities on reddit [[5]](https://reddit.com/r/vaccinelonghaulers){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-5-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}[[6]](https://reddit.com/r/covidlonghaulers){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-6-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}. In addition to people describing the same set of symptoms for both covid- and vaccine long haul, a small Japanese study has shown that a considerable proportion of covid long haulers get worse following vaccination [[7]](https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/jmv.27689){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-7-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}. The people with the **highest antibody response post-vaccination** were the ones who **developed worse symptoms**, perhaps indicating an excessive immune response in this group. Various UK studies show **up to 31% of long covid patients developing worse symptoms after vaccination** [[8]](https://ukhsa.koha-ptfs.co.uk/cgi-bin/koha/opac-retrieve-file.pl?id=fe4f10cd3cd509fe045ad4f72ae0dfff){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-8-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}.

### Community polling in alignment with the studies performed 

This is in line with various covid long haul group polls which tend to show that roughly a third of long haulers report some improvement following vaccination, another third describes symptoms getting worse worse, and the rest reports no change. 

### Wording often dramatic, symptoms not just 'slightly worse', in many cases the descriptions are devastating

It's important to note (and this is often missed in studies) that some people use very dramatic wording when describing their deterioration following vaccination. So it's not just '31% got slightly worse symptoms', it's 31% got worse and a subset possibly got dramatically worse [[9]](https://www.reddit.com/r/covidlonghaulers/comments/nk05qh/so_am_i_the_only_one_not_feeling_better_after_the/){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-9-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}[[10]](https://www.reddit.com/r/covidlonghaulers/comments/thdoia/the_vaccine_made_me_worse/){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-10-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}. **Many commenters** (with a fair share of upvotes) **describe their post-vaccination symptoms being much worse than they ever were post-covid**. To try to stay unbiased here, some long haulers do describe improvements post-vaccination, but the nature of the deteroriation experienced by many makes vaccinating these people without informed consent highly unethical. We do not know when or whether they will recover from these symptoms. Anecdotally, vaccine long haulers often get worse following a covid infection too. The quality of the reddit-pooled data is poor but I assume people are being honest about their symptoms. Given my own experience, this requires little stretch of the imagination.

### Increased risk of hospitalisation in patients vaccinated with a prior covid infection

 A nationwide, retrospective cohort study in the US showed that patients who were **vaccinated after a prior covid infection had increased risk of hospitalisation** by a factor of **2.76** [[11]](https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0264410X22000512){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-11-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}. It's worth noting that this misses possible complications such as long haul, which in general does not lead to immediate hospitalissation. It's also worth noting that CDC acknowledges that waiting longer between mRNA doses may reduce the risk of myocarditis. It stands to reason that the same might apply for covid infection [[12]](https://www.cnbc.com/amp/2022/02/23/cdc-says-waiting-longer-between-pfizer-moderna-doses-may-reduce-myocarditis-risk.html){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-12-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}.

### Vaccines do good, but it's not not 'one-size fits all', informed consent is necessary
I'm for vaccination, but where there is (even a small) risk, there should be freedom of choice. Covid long haul patients should be informed about possible negative consequences of vaccination following long-haul. These adverse events are rare for the (mostly) safe and effective vaccines. But identifying some of the people at-risk may be possible, and worth doing. Professor Warren Tate, a ME/CFS specialist at the University of Otago in NZ has called for exemptions from vaccine mandates for some patients with ME/CFS, citing possible vulnerability to poor sequelae of vaccination. His sentiment is supported by preliminary data from a survey done by the ME/CFS society in NZ, showing a worsening of symptoms without return to baseline in a considerable proportion of patients [[4]](https://www.rnz.co.nz/news/national/456598/expert-says-some-chronic-fatigue-syndrome-sufferers-should-be-exempt-from-covid-19-vaccination){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-4-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}.

### Problem with data collection
Intuitively it would seem to make sense to investigate this with autoimmune disorders in general. Part of the problem is that we are not good at collecting healthcare data. Many symptoms/disorders that can't be immediately identified and diagnosed are dismissed and not reported. We should actively collect and rely more on patient-reported symptoms. Not just for ME/CFS and adverse events to vaccinations, but also f.ex. for women experiencing problems with their menstrual cycle post-vaccination (and presumably post-covid). I can't claim to know that this is happening without data but we could do better with collecting data. 

### Why I mention the VLH onset
I could have simply written that I'm suffering from long covid but it's important to point out the true cause of my symptoms in light of some countries calling for mandatory vaccinations (although this is currently old news). For some of us this is equivalent to mandating disability with ensuing misery for the affected individuals and loss of capital for society in general. 

### Back to the background story and symptoms (move this above?)
My illness starts in June 2021. On the 8th of that month I received my first dose, and my second on the 29th. The effect of the first dose was unremarkable. I wasn't concerned by it as evidenced by my showing up for the second jab 3 weeks later. Following the last dose I experienced various debilitating (and confusing) symptoms, the most meaningful of which I still struggle with every day.

The first thing I remember is getting the worst '**migraine**' I'd ever experienced. I felt like my head was splitting in half and at times my **vision went dark**, as if the lights were being dimmed periodically. 

For the next few months my **blood pressure** was **swinging** up an down, anywhere from 120/80, normal for me, up to ~187/110, and down again. **Resting heartrate**, even lying in bed, was constantly over 110 bpm, and at times this was accompanied by bad **chest pain** and **heart palpitations**. I had **tingling** that went **up the front of my throat/neck**, to the **back of my head**, and to my **ears**. I fainted once and today I still often bend down after standing up to prevent this from reoccurring. 

My ears turned beet-red on a few occasions. I had periodic **tremors in my hands**, and for months I **couldn't sleep for more than 3 hours per night**, as was documented in an in-hospital sleep test a few months later. I had **muscle weakness**. I used to do weight lifting several times per week. I could bench press 125kg (275lbs), but at this point, if I tried to swim a lap in a 25 metre pool I had to stop for a long time to catch my breath and rest. 

When I look at my phone's photos from that period most of the pictures are of my ears, skin, and blood pressure measurements. 

My most debilitating symptoms were the following, I particularly still struggle with the first one: 
- **Complete and total inability to concentrate**, **think**, and **make decisions**
- Periods of bad **anxiet/agitation**, where I would often flood my girlfriend with texts where I speculated what might be wrong
- Periods of the worst **irritability/anger** I've felt, with no logical explanation. My thinking was uncharacteristically violent, I'd 'think expletives' at people I cared about as well as strangers, after which I would think 'wow, something is really wrong here.'. I lost my temper easily. On one occasion a doctor I met suggested the tingling I got was 'muscle tension', but wanted to send me to a cardiologist for the heart symptoms. The latter being a sensible suggestion but I was so annoyed with his explanation of the tingling that I said: 'Simple solution for a simple man' and stormed out, having also refused the appointment with the cardiologist. And even doing *just* this required a great deal of self control.

The anxiety and irritability has since then gotten a lot better, but my inability to concentrate remains. I lost my job early. I was so *out of it*, I couldn't focus on what I was working on. My feeling was that I couldn't think more than 2 simple thoughts per day. I should have contacted my clients and explained my situation to them but this seemed impossible. The project landed on my friend's shoulders with little explanation offered from me. The cognitive load involved in talking to anyone seemed to be too much.

I've always been a hard worker. I was on the dean's list at university where I studied computer science. I worked overtime every day of the week at my first job where I was working as a software contractor for a bank, and I derive much of my self value from my ability to think, work, and make money. 

### Regarding disability
I used to think I would 'kill myself before applying for disability', as I could think of no worse fate than 'becoming a loser', someone who does not contribute to society. And if I tried to explain my current situation to my old self I'm unconvinced that I would be very understanding. I would write much of my actions (and inaction) today off as laziness. Which is why I can't really be too resentful of people not easily understanding where I'm coming from today.

My perspective towards people who are sick and people who are on disability has changed much. I realise now that it's no one's dream to be on disability. You become an outlier in society. You don't feel like you're contributing, it's not desireable by opposite sex, and even people who don't look down on it per se will pity you. Some will have misplaced resentment for your 'time off'. I'm embarrassed by this to the extent where I hesitate/refuse to write this under my own name. I don't want to be seen as a victim. Talking to my friends is not helpful. It mostly serves as a reminder that I'm on timeout from life for the time being. 

### Understanding, communication with friends and family
Describing to my friends what is wrong is complicated, with self-isolation being easier on my mind. I don't want to answer phone calls because it's too much effort. If my phone rings unexpectedly I understand that I will be asked how I'm doing, and my response won't be readily understood. I understand logically that I can't expect anyone to understand something so distant from the reality they've experienced.

What confuses my friends and family is that I am able to talk, I can form sentences, I seem like I'm fine outwardly. But my **entire days are spent lying flat on the couch because sitting upright is too much effort**. It depletes all my energy and I can't think or get anything done. **Contrast this with my previous life where I couldn't lie down to watch TV until late in the evening, preferably after being productive all day and after some exercise.**

 I'm currently more than 2 months late in asking for financial support just because doing it seems like too much effort. I might have to read the contents of a website, compose an email, call someone, do some thinking.. all of which seem like impossible tasks for me. 

When I do talk to my friends I remind them that they would be hard-pressed to find someone more ambitious than me, and that I'm not playing around when I say that I am this ill. That I am unable to do what I say. To work and function. This does help their understanding to a degree but I don't want to spend my time justifying myself or being pitied. I just want my situation acknowledged and preferably ignored. *All my personal time is spent thinking about how to solve these issues* and any off-hand input or questioning is unlikely to be helpful. 

### Avoiding exercise, cognitive load
I do best when I don't exercise. If I walk for more than an hour I experience a flare-up in symptoms. During a flare up, as an example, I may be at the store or pharmacy, but **I can't focus on anything**. I may walk around aimlessly, with no idea what I'm looking for, or what I'm doing. Asking for assistance would be too much effort, so the only option is to go hoome and try again later. **At my worst I can't really make sense of sentences or paragraphs I'm reading**. Sleeping is the only thing that really helps at those times, but I am not fixed or particularly rested after sleep. Just slightly less trashed. 

### Flare ups in symptoms
If I do intense exercise, such as **weightlifting**, my symptoms flare up as follows: 
- I get intense **pressure**/heat inside of my face/**head**
- My body, **limbs**, hands and feet in particular, **go ice-cold** and stay that way for hours
- My **tinnitus** (developed at the start of this) is **sent roaring**
- My **shortness of breath** is exacerbated / more noticeable with little or no straining involved 
- My **thinking** becomes **confused**, I **can't focus, read, or write**
- My **mood** plummets and I get **irritability and/or depression** like I did in the beginning 
- My **muscles tense up**
- The poor thinking in particular **takes days to recover** to the already-subpar baseline

I experience similar symptoms after:
- Eating sugar, this sounds to my prejudiced self as if I just buy into anyone pushing a no-sugar/plant-based diet, but I don't. Sugar makes my symptoms flare up for some reason. Not as intensely as exercise would but enough for me to avoid chocolate for the first time in my life. 
- My ADHD medication, which worked well for me prior to the vaccination now helps for about an hour before triggering a flare-up as described above. This has caused me to avoid the medication from the start.  

### Lost in the beginning
I had no idea how to cope with this. When I got sick I got the feeling that this was out of the ordinary and that I wouldn't receive much help. The only person I felt could help me was me, and I'd never been more poorly equipped to help myself. I shortly gave up on trying to do my job. My girlfriend at the time was in the UK and I'd intended to sort out her car for her while she was abroad. 

The little thinking I did do at the time was not very logical. All I focused on was my girlfriend's car, while half-dead and wondering whether I would die from the symptoms. I'd then lay down in the grass after exertion and rest, and when at home I'd try my best to do research and read about my symptoms. 

### Relationshpi with my ex
I suggested to my girlfriend that we take a break because I saw that how I was feeling was making her feel bad. We eventually broke up. I love and appreciate her still, but I'm happy she hasn't had to sit around and see me go through this process, or see how I'm doing today, even if somewhat improved moodwise. 

### Losing my job
I shortly realised I would not be getting another job unless I'd find a solution for my symptoms. A couple of months in I did find that I'd developed hyperthyroidism which I opted to have definitive treatment for, in the form of surgery. It took me much too long to realise and decide on this because it felt like I **couldn't think or make decisions**. I couldn't bring myself to go to the doctor or ask for testing. 

### Surgery and moving abroad, trying to power through
In the weeks after my surgery some of the irritability and perhaps particularly agitation seemed to subside to a degree, but I still couldn't think, or exercise. I flew to the UK and spent more than half a year in London to give myself a change of scenery. I wanted to be able to focus on recovery without being reminded every day that I was no longer participating in society like my friends and colleagues, and that I was no longer with the girlfriend who I loved. In London I did some exploring, I tried weight-lifting, climbing, and running. Both lifting and running made my symptoms worse, and excessively long walks seemed bad for my cognition too. But on a positive note.. the restaurants in London are amazing. Particularly I liked the amount of Korean restaurants. We happen to have a shortage of those where I'm from. Amazon next-day delivery is pretty good too. 

### Finding people with the same set of symptoms
Earlier on I'd found people with symptoms identical to mine through youtube interviews, and eventually I'd gotten into the online support groups and communities. I've added embedded YT videos of interviews with people with post-vaccine long haul down in the references [[15]](#vlh-1){:class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-15-highlights&quot;}[[16]](#vlh-2){:class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-16-highlights&quot;}. It's been insightful to read about other peoples experiences to see the different (but largely similar) presentation of symptoms. It also helped me to realise that, although my reaction to the vaccine is rare, I am not alone in this. 

After noting that some people in these groups tended to get worse with exercise, in some cases without returning to their new baseline of symptoms, I decided to take it easy with the workouts for the time being. It already seemed like trying to power-through wasn't delivering much for me. 

### My symptoms today
This brings us to today, the 6th of April 2022. 

I've tried various treatments with varying degrees of success at this point. 

**All my waking**/lucid **hours are spent reading research papers**, **reading about other peoples experiences and symptoms**, and generally looking for possible solutions.

Many of my physical symptoms I did manage to get under control to a great degree early on, but **my concentration and thinking remains poor**. I also still get much worse with exercise and ADHD medication. 

Status today: 
- Tingling and numbness is largely gone, unless symptoms are flaring up
- Tinnitus is gone, - unless flare up 
- Ears are not turning beet-red anymore
- I don't get the agitation I did early on 
- I sleep longer, unless my symptoms are flaring 
- My blood pressure is not swinging wildly
- My resting heartrate are fine unless I'm flaring up 
- **I cannot sit upright for more than a few minutes at a time withoutu getting exhausted**
- I cannot accomplish easy tasks or function as a person 
- I **cannot concentrate at all**
- I cannot live a normal life for the time being

### Brief comparison with the CLH symptoms

It may be interesting at this point to compare my list of symptoms with the symptoms of covid long haul as described by the CDC [[13]](https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/long-term-effects/index.html){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-13-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}. My symptoms align fairly well with other long haulers. Largely the symptoms could be split up into 'neurological, cardiovascular, and dysautonomia (neuro again)'. These are broadly the symptom categories all long haulers deal with, how much each category weighs for any given person varies greatly. 

### Things looking up to an extent, brain semi-functional behind the scenes 

To add some tentative positivity to this, **in the past month, I've been able to have days where I can be productive. I can think, perform tasks, and I can write software**. This is a **huge deal**, as I've wondered for most of this time **whether my brain was totally gone**, the most suitable way I found to explain my symptoms to anyone is that I **feel like I've had a stroke**, that's how impaired my thinking feels.

So seeing that my brain can still work under any conditions is a big deal to me. *The caveat is that it's only possible with the help of medications, and they seem to put a great strain on my body. So I am hesitant to do this for extended periods, I only do this when I must get something done.* 

**The rest of this post will go into blood tests and medications I've tried, some research I've done and my thoughts on it, as well as what I make of my future prospects. It might not be very interesting for anyone outside the 'Long Haul' community. Unless the reader is a big nerd.**

## Consider writing about VLH/CLH after your whole story -- the set of symptoms -- similarity with CLH - the impact on peoples lives (as per facebook and reddit) 

---

# Testing, treatments and results so far (consider only a brief description here, with details in a follow-up post, as well as possible treatment targets)

&amp;gt; Brief disclaimer: No one should imitate what I describe below. The methods mentioned are potentially dangerous and could lead to injury, permanent disability, or death. Always consult your physician.   

&amp;gt; My intention is to slowly add to this post, an exhaustive list of symptoms experienced by long haulers, studies, possible etiologies, possible treatments, and my own experiments and results. This will probably take some time, and I can only write this while medicated, adding further delay. 

&amp;gt; Anything that worked for me will not necessarily work for the reader. Even though there are broad similarities in the presentation of symptoms between most long haulers they aren't the same and the causes will likely vary. I believe the variation in presentation depends on where we get injured. It's well documented that the spike protein causes endothelial dysfunction [[14]](https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33360731/){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-14-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}. How this damage presents in the individual depends on where it occurs. If it's in the veins/around the kidney, it could cause dysfunction and symptoms related to renal impairment (which on its own, can be quite broad and confusing). Potentially some hypoxia and nerve damage could happen in the brain, with symptoms showing up in a variety of ways. This is why every stroke patient or patient with traumatic brain injury can present with just about any symptom under the sun. We're not all the same and the symptoms will depend on location, severity, and our body's response to the injury. 

# My own blood test results
Early on in my illness I had several blood tests. Most of them were unremarkable. Liver function tests were normal, the majority of kidney tests including electrolytes and creatinine were normal. Lipids (total cholesterol, LDL, HDL, and triglycerides) were consistently under the reference range. Which is unspecific but consistent with hyperthyroidism. High cholesterol on the contrary is common in hypothyroidism. 

Early on I detected subclinical hyperthyroidism, with TSH entirely suppressed but FT4 and FT3 within range. Eventually this progressed to overt hyperthyroidism, with FT4 and FT3 very elevated, and I had a thyroidectomy for this. Complete blood count was broadly fine, ferritin low-normal, cortisol also low-normal, which some might say is unusual in the presence of hyperthyroidism but adrenal stimulation testing was fine. 

I had some discolouration of the skin on my chest and between my eyebrows (loss of colour) that persists but hasn't gotten worse. 

I was most curious about vaccine-induced autoimmunity, and thus I had the following tests: 

TPO antibodies (such as those seen in Hashimotos hypothyroidism and Graves) slightly elevated on 2 occasions, fine in another laboratory. ANCA antibodies present but not elevated (Lupus, often associated with kidney damage). RF slightly elevated. Anti-phospholipid antibodies present but not elevated, clotting factors all normal. ds-DNA (primarily associated with Lupus) also present but not elevated. ANA very low in the range.RF-IgG slightly elevated. Adrenal cortex antibodies not detected, making primary AI via autoimmmunity unlikely. 

On numerous occasions since then I've tested my AM cortisol, and it consistently comes back at around 150-200 nmol/L, which is low-normal, and in the 'equivocal' range [[3]](https://www.ouh.nhs.uk/biochemistry/tests/tests-catalogue/cortisol.aspx){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-3-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}. With both negative ACA and a synacthen stimulation test showing normal adrenal response to synthetic ACTH there's little to indicate overt adrenal insufficiency. Hydrocortisone supplementation (very low dose) has still been beneficial for my symptoms, including mood, joint pain, and general flare-ups. Doses that are too high seem to magnify my tinnitus. If I don't take any I seem to get worse joint pain, some itching, and worse cognitive symptoms. 

I noted early on, shortly after June 2021, that many of my physical symptoms seemed to get worse with eating, in particular when I ate something containing **potassium**. Since I suspected that this was the case, I restricted my diet quite a bit which likely influenced the test results that followed. 

Despite the interventions I made, '**hyperkalemia**' was detected on 3 occasions, with 3 additional tests showing kalium within the reference range range. The reason for testing potassium was that a lot of my early symptoms were consistent with hyperkalemia. Including **tiredness, weakness, numbness, tingling, nausea, shortness of breath, chest pain,** and **palpitations** [[1]](https://www.healthline.com/health/high-potassium-hyperkalemia#symptoms){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-1-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}.

**Fludrocortisone was helpful** for me with managing these symptoms, up to 0.3mg/daily helped me not having to be as limited with my diet. I could eat some potassium without tingling/chest pain and palpitations coming on. If I stopped the medicine my sensitivity to these foods increased again. 

In addition to the hyperkalemia described above I also had a urine test that was slightly alkaline, which could indicate a compensatory mechanism for a state of acidosis.  

Since then I've dropped fludrocortisone but I still think it's worth noting. Fludrocortisone is typically used for adrenal insufficiency (primary), to replace aldosterone. It increases sodium retention and decreases potassium, having only a mild alkolytic effect if potassium depletion is prevented (extrapolating from aldosterone suppl. result) [[2]](https://jasn.asnjournals.org/content/11/2/369){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-2-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}. It's also sometimes used off-label to treat orthostatic hypotension, which is a common complaint among long haulers [[13]](https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/long-term-effects/index.html){:target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-targ=&quot;.citation-13-highlights&quot; class=&quot;trigger-modal&quot;}.

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">My experience with debilitating illness (long haul) and potential treatments</summary></entry></feed>